Guide to the Harris L. Kimball papers, circa 1973-2003.
Kimball, Harris L. papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Harris L. Kimball papers, circa 1973-2003.
7823
Harris L. Kimball
4 cubic feet.
Legal Documents, Correspondence, Photocopies.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Records of the landmark cases in which Mr. Kimball represented various clients and other files and ephemera about Kimball.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Harris L. Kimball was the first openly gay attorney in the US. In 1955, while working as a civil rights lawyer in Florida, he was arrested for "lewd and lascivious conduct" with another man. He was disbarred on September 6, 1957. On July 3, 1973, the New York Court of Appeals found Kimball to be of good character and qualified to practice law in New York State. In "Sexuality and the Law: An Encyclopedia of Major Legal Cases" (Garland, 1993), Arthur S. Leonard highlights the significant role this decision by the NY Court of Appeals played "in the gradual recognition that lesbian and gay people were entitled to full citizenship rights in a diverse society."
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Records of the landmark cases in which Mr. Kimball represented various clients and other files and ephemera about Kimball.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Kimball, Harris L.
Subjects:
Litigation.; Actions and defenses.; Procedural law.; Civil rights.; Homosexuality
Places:
United States; New York (State)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Collecting program: Human Sexuality Collection.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Florida Bar Disbarment Court Case Related Materials
Series II. New York State Bar Related Materials
Series III. Assorted Court Case Materials
Series IV. Assorted Correspondence and Writing
Series V. Assorted Materials
CONTAINER LIST
- Florida Bar Disbarment Court Case Related Materials, 1956-1983
  - State of Florida/Florida Bar v. Kimball Documents, Expression (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Miscellaneous loose documents and a fragmentary bound document
  - Florida Bar v. Kimball, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Report of the Florida Bar Grievance Committee for the Ninth Judicial Circuit regarding the Florida Bar v. Harris Kimball (photocopy)
  - Kimball v. Florida Bar et al. - Case No. 74-688-Civ-NCR(WM) Court Documents, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Assorted documents from both the plaintiff, Harris Kimball, and the defendents, The Florida Bar, et al., including a notice of appeal to the Fifth Circuit court.
  - Kimball v. Florida Bar et al. - Case No. 75-1005 (Fifth Circuit) Court Documents, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Assorted documents from both the appellant Harris Kimball, and the appellees, The Florida Bar, et al., including a copy of the Appellant's Appendix and photocopies from Law Journals on the case's outcome
  - Kimball v. Florida Bar et al. - Case No. 74-668-Civ-NCR Court Documents, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Assorted documents from both the plaintiff, Harris Kimball, and the defendents, The Florida Bar, et al.; also included are photocopies of the verdict from the Federal Case Reporter 'Federal Supplement'
  - Kimball v. Florida Bar et al. - Case No. 79-1781 Court Documents, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Assorted documents from both the appellant Harris Kimball, and the appellees, The Florida Bar, et al., including a transcript from the court and an excerpt of records
  - Kimball v. Florida Bar - Case No. CRE82001(60,831), 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Documents from Kimball's petition for reinstatement to the Florida Bar
  - Kimball v. Florida Bar - Case No. CRE82001(60,831), 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    A petition for review opened by Kimball against the Florida Bar
  - Kimball v. Florida Bar Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Mostly between Harris Kimball and his attorneys, Louis Jepeway and Jeremiah Gutman, regarding Kimball's case against the Florida Bar over his disbarrment and petition for reinstatement.
  - Kimball v. Florida Bar Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Kimball v. Florida Bar Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Kimball v. Florida Bar Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Reference statutes and cases - Reinstatement Petition of Harris Kimball, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes a respondent brief from The Florida Bar v. Ronald Kay (Case No. 38,694); an amicus curiae from Joseph Acanfora v. Board of Education of Montgomery County, et al.; and documents from Case No. 59,238 (Florida Board of Bar Examiners: in re N.R.S)
  - The Florida Bar Reinstatement Manual - March 1981, 1981-03 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- New York State Bar Related Materials, 1957-1988
  - New York State Bar Admission Petition Court Documents, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Documents from Kimball's application to the New York Bar; includes the stenographer's minutes from May 31, 1972.
  - New York State Bar Admission Petition Court Documents, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - New York State Bar Application - Appendix (Original), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    A fragmentary bound edition of the appendix from Kimball's petition to the New York State Bar
  - New York State Bar Application - Appendix (Photocopy), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - New York State Bar Admission Petition Court Documents, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes documents from 1974 and undated items associated with Kimball's petition for admission to the New York State Bar
  - New York State Bar Admission Petition Correspondence and Documents, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Contains copies of Kimball's various verdicts regarding his admission to the New York State Bar as seen in the Appellate Division Reports, 2d Series; the New York Reports, 2d Series; and the New York State Law Digest
  - Reference statutes and cases - New York State Bar Admission Petitiom, 1957-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Certificate from the New York State Eastern District Court, 1974-04-05 (Box 5)
    Issued by the Eastern District of New York State, signed by Lewis Orgel on April 5, 1974, to Harris Kimball; verifies that Kimball was admitted and qualified as an Attorney and Counselor to the Eastern District of New York State
  - Certificate from the New York State Southern District Court, 1974-04-05 (Box 5)
    Issued by the Southern District of New York State, signed by Raymond Burghardt on April 04, 1974, to Harris Kimball; verifies that Kimball was admitted and qualified as an Attorney and Counselor to the Southern District of New York State
  - Westchester County Bar Association 1987-1988 Pictorial Directory, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    Harris Kimball is listed on page 68 and 118
- Assorted Court Case Materials, 1954-1994
  - Gregory Clark and William Bolt Transcript - Jan. 18, 1980 (Copy 1), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Gregory Clark and William Bolt Transcript - Jan. 18, 1980 (Copy 2), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Gregory Clark and William Bolt Transcript - Jan. 18, 1980 (Copy 3), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Gregory Clark and William Bolt Transcript - Feb. 13, 1980 (Copy 1), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Gregory Clark and William Bolt Transcript - Feb. 13, 1980 (Copy 2), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Gregory Clark and William Bolt Transcript - April 21, 1980 (Copy 1), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Gregory Clark and William Bolt Transcript - April 21, 1980 (Copy 2), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Gregory Clark and William Bolt Court Documents, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Assorted legal documents associated with the case against Clark and Bolt
  - Gregory Clark Miscellaneous Documents and Correspondence, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Documents and correspondence regarding Clark's individual case against the state of New York
  - John Spinelli and Bruno Stra Court Documents, 1978;1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Joseph P.' and 'Donald B.' Documents and Correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Assorted Spinelli and Stra Documents and Correspondence, 1978-1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - White Plains Railroad Station Arrests Documents and Correspondence, 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Peter Sidone Court Documents and Assorted Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Miscellaneous items associated with the case against Peter Sidone in Port Chester, NY
  - The People of NYS v. Michael Garr Documents, 1975; 1978 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Michael Garr v. State of New York Court Documents, 1977; 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 17-19)
  - Assorted Michael Garr Documents, 1975-1980 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Includes a copy of the Last Will and Testement of Michael Garr and various correspondence regarding Michael Garr v. State
  - Ardsley Service Area Assorted, 1978-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Miscellaneous photographs, newspaper articles, and transcriptions of telephone conversations regarding the Ardsley Service Area arrests and trials
  - Gay Activists Alliance Court Documents and Correspondence, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Includes court documents regarding the GAA picketing a private residence, newspaper clippings, various correspondence, and the documents' original folder with notes.
  - Thomas Kingman Miscellaneous Documents and Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Includes a copy of the interview with Thomas Kingman from August 21, 1978, newspaper clippings, and correspondence.
  - Gretchen Grant v. John Doyle et al. Court Documents, 1972; 1974; 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Assorted Cases, 1980-1981; 1983-1985; 1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Includes documents and/or correspondence from "The People of the State of New York State v. Wei Chen", "Joseph Harmon v. James Reap", "The People of the State of New York v. John Colern", "The People of the State of New York v. Evelyn Gutherie", "The People of the State of New York v. Peter Cannizzaro", "The People of the State of New York v. Stuart Heller and Donald Paschall", and a letter from Danny Mauariky(?),
  - Reference Cases and Statutes, 1954-1985 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
- Assorted Correspondence and Writing, 1953-2012
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1953-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Handwritten notes spanning Kimball's career on assorted topics; most are undated
  - Sodomy and the Constitution (c.1975), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    An excerpt of Sodomy and the Constitution by Walter Barnett prepared by Kimball in 1987, which is missing page 46
  - Sodomy and the Constitution Footnotes, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    The footnotes for the excerpt of Sodomy and the Constitution by Walter Barnett; also included is a section of a Memorandum of Law on homosexuals, which Kimball derived from Sodomy and the Constitution
  - "The Emerging Gay Lawyer" Correspondendce and Drafts, 1954; 1961-1965; 1969-1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Assorted newspaper and magazine articles, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Articles either relating to Harris Kimball, his cases and clients, or to homosexuality (in the workplace, the perception of, etc.).
  - Assorted newspaper and magazine articles, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Assorted newspaper and magazine articles, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Assorted newspaper and magazine articles, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Assorted newspaper and magazine articles, 1990-2004 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Articles either relating to Harris Kimball, his cases and clients, or to homosexuality (in the workplace, the perception of, etc.); some are undated.
  - WBAI Radio Documents and Correspondence, 1990-1997;2001;2004 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Folio editions from November 1984, December 1984, January 1985 (x2), March 1985, April 1985, March 1986, September 1986, and April 1986.
  - WBAI Folioand other articles on WBAI Radio, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Harris L. Kimball: America's 'First' Gay Lawyer" drafts, 1991; Conkey, Kathleen (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "An American Original." Harris Kimball (Short Excerpts), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Contains three excerpts from "An American Original" with Kimball's brief intro and copies of his correspondence with a Wall Street Journal Editor
  - Excerpt from "An American Original", 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
  - "The Abominable and Detestable Crime", Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    A draft copy of the article with both editor notation and author notes for future edits
  - Harris Kimball Memoir, 2001-2007 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Email correspondence between Harris Kimball and Robert Herrig(?) regarding Kimball's memoir and some mention of Kimball's will; working drafts for the memoir; research articles on memoir writing
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2001;2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Documents, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Documents, 1990-1994 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Documents, 1994-1999 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Documents, 2000-2012 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Undated Correspondence and Assorted Documents, Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "Of a Homosexual Teacher" from the Texas Southern Law Review, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - New York State Department of Health: AIDS Institute, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - "Sociomedical Research Priorities in AIDS (Draft)", 1985; Martin, John (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "This Project of New York Gay Law Students: Panel Discussion" presented by Rutgers S.B.A., Undated (Box 5)
  - "Homosexuals in revolt" article, 1971-12-31; Durham, Michael (Box 5)
    From LIFE: 12/31/1971; Pulled from 2-9
- Assorted Materials, 1944, 1968, 1975
  - Tabula 1944, Oak Park and River Forest Township Highschool yearbook, 1944 (Box 5)
    Harris Kimball's highschool yearbook from his senior year, including a 'Program of Special Services for Class of 1944'
  - Portrait of Harris Kimball, Undated (Box 5)
    Possibly his senior portrait, taken at Toloff Studios in Evanston/Oak Park, Illinois
  - Diploma from University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign awarded to Harris Kimball, 1968-02-01 (Box 5)
    Awarding the degree of Juris Doctor on February 1, 1968; issued to replace an LL.B. degree awarded August 20, 1951
  - Certificate from the United States Tax Court awarded to Harris Kimball, 1975-11-06 (Box 5)
    Issued by Howard Dawson, Jr granting permission for Harris Kimball to practice in the United States Tax Court
  - Legal Observer armband, Undated (Box 5)
    Armband with 'LEGAL OBSERVER' written with patches, with lambda-esque patches to the right and left of 'LEGAL"; the item itself is made of demin and black felt; the article appears handstitched
  - T-Shirt with iron-on transfer of a news article, Undated (Box 5)
    The article is from the New York Times: June 27, 2003, " Justices, 6-3, Legalizes Gay Sexual Conduct in Sweeping Reversal of Court's '86 Ruling"